Welcome to the final video of this week.
In this video, we will discuss some popular safety frameworks,
some of which we encountered in the last lesson.
More specifically, we will describe some generic,
analytical frameworks including fault trees,
failure modes and effects analyses or FMEA,
and hazard and operability analysis or HAZOP.
Then we will focus on
automotive and autonomous safety frameworks and discuss functional safety or FUSA,
and safety of intended functionality, or SOTIF.
We'll define these terms later on in the video.
Let's begin. We'll start off with fault tree analysis.
Fault trees can be used as a preliminary analysis framework,
and can be steadily expanded to encompass as much details necessary.
Fault trees are top-down flows in which we
analyze a possible failure of a system to be avoided,
and then identify all of the ways in which it can
occur from events and failures at lower levels of the system.
The top node in a fault tree is the root or top event.
The intermediate nodes in the fault tree are logic gates,
that define possible causes for the root event.
The decomposition continues to a level of detail
for which a probability of such an event can be defined.
The fault tree can then be analyzed by combining
the probabilities using the laws of Boolean logic.
To assess the overall probability of
root cause event and the causes that most contribute to its occurrence.
Let's consider a simple example,
and take a car crash as our root event.
The cause of a car crash could be broken down
into either a software failure or a hardware failure,
amongst many other possibilities that we've
described as hazard classes in our earlier videos.
Very crudely, the hardware failure could be because of
manufacturing defects or material imperfections, for example.
Similarly, a software error could be due to
malfunctioning perception code or some cybersecurity problem,
say, if we were hacked.
From there, we can proceed to software subsystems and
specific calculations within those subsystems
deepening the tree at each successive branching.
Ultimately, we'll arrive at specific failure rates for which we can
assign probabilities of occurrence per hour or per mile of operation.
We have now arrived at the leaf nodes of the fault tree.
Then using the logic gates structure,
we can explicitly compute statistics of
overall failure rates given assessments of the individual leaf node failure rates.
The operations used to propagate these probabilities upwards would
be the same as the rules of probability when events follow set theory.
So, for example, for independent events,
the OR and AND probabilities would be the sum or product of children node probabilities.
This is the general idea behind fault trees,
which are referred to as probabilistic fault trees,
when probabilities are included at the leaf nodes.
Probabilistic fault trees are a top-down approach to safety
that has been widely used in the nuclear and aerospace industries,
and can similarly be applied to autonomous driving.
The challenge lies in building a comprehensive tree and
incorrectly identifying the probabilities of the leaf node events.
Let's now look at FMEA,
which stands for failure modes and effects analyses.
Whereas fault trees flow down from a system failure to all of its possible causes,
FMEA is a bottom-up process that looks at
individual causes and determines all the possible effects that might occur.
Often, FTA's and FMEA's are used together to assess safety critical systems.
Failure modes are modes or ways in which
a particular component of the overall system can cause the system to fail.
Effects analysis refers to analyzing all
of the possible effects these mode failures can cause.
Often, the effects analysis seeks to identify
those modes that bring about the most critical failures,
which can then lead to improved designs that add
more redundancy or higher reliability to the system.
Let's come to the big idea behind FMEA.
The goal is to categorize failure modes by priority.
So, we ask questions like,
how serious are the effects,
how frequently do these failures happen,
and how easy is it to detect these failures?
Then we quantify all the failures using priority values,
then we start addressing the failures with the highest priority first.
Here are the steps. The goal is to construct a table of all possible risky situations,
and we start off by,
first discussing with field experts and
identifying processes at the level of detail we want in the table.
Then, we question the purpose of the system and list all failure possibilities.
Then for each failure possibility,
we identify the possible consequences and assign
each consequence a severity rating between one and 10,
10 being the most severe.
For each consequence, we identify the possible root causes,
and for each route cause,
we assign another number between one and 10,
to denote how frequently this cause occurs.
Then, we identify all the ways in which the failure mode can be detected by operator,
maintenance, inspection, or a fault detection system.
We assess the overall mode detection likelihood before
it causes an effect and assign another score from 1-10,
with one being guaranteed to be detected and 10 being impossible to detect.
Finally, we compute a final number called the risk priority number,
which is the product of the severity,
the occurrence, and the detection.
The higher this value is,
the higher the priority is.
Eventually, we address the most problematic failure modes by modifying
our implementation of the system until we reduce the risks to an acceptable level.
It is also possible to perform FMEA with
actual failure probabilities as in fault tree analysis,
and to define acceptable risk levels in terms of
the likelihood of a critical event occurring over a fixed period of operation.
The method doesn't change just the meaning of
the numbers and the complexity of completing the entire analysis.
Let's stick with the simple scoring approach and make
the FMEA process more concrete with a brief example.
Consider, a specific failure where the vehicle has driven
onto a gravel patch that appears in its test area due to road construction,
which leads to controller instability.
The worst-case effect could be a physical crash,
which would be severity 10.
It might also lead to driver discomfort,
or a near miss,
but these would be lower severity events.
This event could happen regularly in urban environments
wherever construction of a particular type occurs.
So, it is somewhat likely.
Let's say we're able to assess the occurrence number at four.
Similarly, we can assign a current scores to the other effects.
Let's assume this problem is not currently detectable as
the road surface texture is not actively
monitored during operation of our autonomy software.
So, detectability would be at number 10 for all of these effects.
The risk priority number for a crash would then be 10 times 4 times 10, which is 400.
In the same way, we could have other failure modes as well.
A sign perception failure with the priority number of a 100, let's say,
a GPS synchronization failure with a priority number of 300,
and maybe a vehicle motion prediction failure with the priority of 150.
So, we would go about addressing these failures in
implementation by focusing on driving on gravel than GPS failure,
than motion prediction, and finally sign perception.
And so this is the general framework behind FMEA.
FMEA is a risk assessment idea that was developed by
the military and aerospace industries and later brought to the automotive industry.
It provides a really structured way to quantify risks and deal with them.
The most important first.
Lastly, a common variation on FMEA that appears frequently,
is the Hazard and Operability Study or HAZOP.
HAZOP is more of a qualitative process as compared to FMEA,
where we seek to define the risks quantitatively.
So, in HAZOP, the main purpose is to
brainstorm effectively over the set of possible hazards that can arise.
For complex processes, the risks can be assessed
without having to assign specific values to occurrence,
severity and detection, which may be hard to do.
HAZOP is often used earlier in the design process to guide the conceptual design phase.
The key addition in HAZOP is that,
guide words are used to lead the brainstorm applied to each system requirement.
These guide words include things like not, more, less,
early, late and lead to possible failure modes that might not otherwise be considered.
So think of HAZOP as a simplified ongoing FMEA brainstorming approach.
Let's now focus on a more specific type of safety and discuss
existing safety frameworks for automotive and low-level autonomy feature development,
which are often used in assessing hardware and software failures in autonomous vehicles.
In particular, let's discuss the functional safety approach
described in ISO 26262 and the safety of
intended functionality approach which extends on ISO to
26262 and is defined in ISOPAR 21448.1.
We won't be able to go into significant detail on either process,
but I've included links to supplemental materials, if you'd like to learn more.
Functional Safety or FUSA,
is the absence of unreasonable risk from
malfunctioning behavior caused by failures of the hardware and software in a car,
or unintended behaviors arising with respect to its intended design.
The ISO 262 standard defines functional safety terms and
activities for electrical and electronic systems within motor vehicles.
As such, addresses only the hardware and software hazards
that can affect autonomous vehicle safety.
The standard defines four Automotive Safety Integrity Levels or ASIL.
With ASIL D being the most stringent and A being the least.
Each level has associated with it specific development requirements,
that must be adhered to for certification.
The functional safety process follows a V-shaped flow.
Starting at the top left with requirements specification then analysis
of hazards and risks and proceeding to implementation of functionality.
We then climb up the right branch to confirm the design goals have been met.
We start with low-level verifications such as software unit tests,
and then proceed to subsystem and full system validation through simulation,
test track, operations and on-road testing.
As we descend the V on the left,
high-level requirements turn into low-level implementations.
And as we climb the V on the right,
we confirm each low-level function implementation before
combining them to confirm system requirements for safe operation.
The final step is a summary functional safety assessment,
to evaluate residual risk and
determine if our system has reached an acceptable level of safety.
At the start of the functional safety V,
we use HARA or Hazard and Risk Assessment.
In HARA, we identify and categorize
hazardous events and specify requirements to avoid unreasonable risk.
This process drives all of the system development and testing beyond this point.
To do so, we first identify possible hardware and software
faults or malfunctions and unintended functions that can affect car safety.
This is where FMEA or HAZOP are used in
the functional safety framework and leads to a specific set of hazards to our system.
We then define a list of scenarios or situations that
the system must operate in drawing on our ODD to create this list.
Next, we combine hazards and situations into hazardous events, describe expected damages,
and determine risk parameters,
to calculate numerical values of
potential risk for each combination of situation and hazard.
After the risk assessment,
we choose the highest risk scenarios.
The worst-case events that can happen with respect to each possible malfunction.
Then finally, we define our safety requirements based on these worst-case scenarios.
The HARA process sets the design goals for the system in
a way that is aware of all of the worst-case failures that can occur.
Through validation confirms that
these worst-case failures are handled with only reasonable risk.
And this is the main idea behind functional safety.
You focus on worst-case requirements and then implement
hardware and software that can at least handle these worst-case requirements.
Finally, let's briefly explore the Safety of Intended Functionality Standard or SOTIF,
which is formally defined in the ISOPAS 21448 document.
SOTIF is specifically concerned with failure causes related to
system performance limitations and predictable misuse of the system.
Performance limitations or insufficiencies of the implemented functions due
to technology limitations such as sensor performance limitations and noise,
or limitations of algorithms such as
object detection failures and limitations of actuator technology.
Hardware and software failures are addressed by
the functional safety standard in ISO 26262 and are out of the scope of SOTIF.
SOTIF also addresses unsafe actions due to foreseeable misuse by the user.
Such as user confusion,
user overload and user overconfidence.
The current SOTIF standard targets automation levels,
zero, one and two.
It also states that its methods can be applied to levels three,
four, and five autonomy but additional measures may be required.
SOTIF can be seen as an extension of the functional safety process,
specifically designed to address the challenges of automated driving functions.
As such, it follows very much the same V-shaped development philosophy,
but with augmented components.
SOTIF also employs HARA to identify
the hazards that arise from performance limitations and misuse.
And then performs a similar sequence of design,
unit testing and verification and validation,
to confirm the safety requirements have been met.
If you'd like to dive deeper into either the functional safety or SOTIF standards,
please check out the links in the supplemental materials.
Let's summarize what we've learned about in this video.
We started off with a discussion of generic safety frameworks.
Fault tree analysis as a top-down approach to
safety assessment and failure modes
and effects analysis as a bottom-up approach to safety.
Then we discussed the ideas of functional safety which are used commonly in
software and hardware risk assessments and
discussed SOTIF as an extension to functional safety,
that accounts for performance limitations and misuse.
All of these ideas are used a lot in the industry,
as we saw with both Waymo and GM which use
nearly all of these techniques in their safety assessments.
Congratulations.
You've made it to the end of this safety assessment module.
Let's summarize what we learned this week.
We started off with discussions on why safety is important specifically how
a broad range of distinct failures can lead to self-driving accidents.
Then we formally defined safety concepts and discussed
the NHTASA's safety recommendations for autonomous vehicles.
We then discussed how Waymo and GM think about self-driving safety.
Then we described analytic and data-driven approaches to demonstrating safety.
Finally, in today's video,
we discussed common safety assessment frameworks.
Including fault trees, failure modes and effects analysis,
functional safety and safety of intended functionality.
Hopefully, this week give you insight into designing
safe self-driving systems and into properly assessing the systems you built.
Before we wrap up this week,
we'll have a discussion with
Professor Krzysztof Czarnecki from the University of Waterloo,
an expert on autonomous safety assessment.
I have lots of interesting questions to ask. Stay tuned.