[MUSIC]
Now that you've had a chance to do some
controller design and perform simulations
with Carla, we will show you our
solution to the final course assessment.
Recall that our reference signal
consists of both speed and position.
So we will require both longitudinal and
lateral control.
For longitudinal control we
implemented a PID Controller
which was described in the module
on longitudinal control.
This PID controller will take
the desired speed as the reference and
outputs throttle and brick.
As the desired speeds
are reasonably low and
steady, we bypass the low
level controller entirely.
Remember that a PID controller
consists of three components.
First, a pure gain Kp that
scales the vehicle acceleration
based on the speed error.
This ensures that the vehicle is
accelerating in the correct direction
with the magnitude
proportional to the error.
Second in integral term KI sets up the
output based on accumulated past errors.
This ensures the steady steed errors
are eliminated for ramp referencing.
Finally, the derivative term
KD dampens the overshoot
caused by the integration term.
To complete the longitudinal control,
we must convert the acceleration
output from the PID controller
into throttle and brake commands.
For simplicity,
positive outputs will be throttle and
negative outputs will correspond to break.
For lateral control,
we implement the Stanley controller that
you learned about on lateral control.
Since the reference signal
given are waypoint positions,
we need to convert them into cross
track errors and heading errors.
We use the current way point, and the past
way point to generate the trajectory line.
Then, using the equation of this line,
we determine the perpendicular
distance to the front axle.
This is our cross track error.
We can now convert the cross track
error into part of our steering input
by multiplying a gain k.
Dividing by the current velocity and
taking the inverse tangent.
To calculate the heading error we
subtract the current vehicle yard from
the trajectory line angle.
The trajectory line angle can be
calculated by taking the inverse tangent
of it's slope.
Adding both the steering derived
from the cross track error and
the heading error gives us
the total steering input.
This completes our lateral controller.
Combining both the longitudinal and
lateral controllers gives us the following
speed profile and trajectory.
As you can see, the controller
tracks the reference speed well and
follows the path with very little error.
There are of course other controllers
that you could of implemented
to solve this project as well.
Such as pure pursuit, feet forward
control, and model predictive control.
If you've implemented these controllers
let us know how they performed.
Congratulations you have now completed
the final project for this course.
This is a huge milestone on your
journey to becoming engineers for
self driving cars.
You will be able to employ
your new simulation and
control algorithm design skills
throughout the autonomous driving space.
So keep up the great work.
We hope applying what you've learned
throughout this course in a real world
programming scenario has been
an enjoyable learning experience.
You're going to learn a lot more
about what it takes to programming
a self-driving car in the subsequent
courses in this specialization.
[MUSIC]