Welcome to this week's first lesson.
In the previous module,
we learned some basic
longitudinal control
for autonomous car
controlled development.
In this module, we will go
through the lateral control.
We will cover four lessons this week.
In the first lesson,
we'll see the introduction
to lateral vehicle control.
In lessons two and three,
we'll introduce
two geometric path following
control strategies that are built on
the no-slip assumption
of kinematic modeling.
Finally, in the last lesson,
we will focus on
model predictive control,
as an example of
an advanced control strategy
regularly used in
autonomous vehicles.
In this lesson specifically,
we'll introduce the core concepts
needed to perform lateral control,
and you'll learn how to define
different types of
reference path and how
to compute heading and
crosstrack errors relative
to those reference paths.
So, let's get started.
One of the main concerns in
autonomous vehicles is ensuring
the vehicle can precisely
follow a predefined path,
executing the motion plan
devised in the higher level
planning module.
This is the main goal of
lateral control which must select
the steering angle required
to correct any errors that accumulate
and track changes in the path
direction as they appear.
To design the lateral controller,
we need to define the error between
the vehicle position and the
appropriate desired path coordinates,
select a control design strategy
that drives errors to
zero while still satisfying
steering angle limits,
and consider the dynamic limitations
of vehicle and desired
ride characteristics such as
maximum lateral acceleration
and minimum jerk.
Control command must be cognizant
of the available tire forces and
not exceed the capabilities of
the vehicle when correcting
for tracking errors.
The reference path is
a fundamental interface
between the planning system
in the lateral controller,
and can be defined in multiple ways.
The easiest approach is
to define a sequence of
straight line segments by requiring
a sequence of end point vertices
that are connected linearly.
This path definition can be very
compact and easy to construct,
assuming points are well spaced and
the environment allows for
mostly straight line motion,
as in a Manhattan grid of roadways.
However, the path includes
heading discontinuities,
which make precise tracking
a challenge with a steered vehicle.
A refinement of the line
segment approach is to
provide a series of
tightly spaced waypoints.
This spacing is usually fixed in
terms of distance or travel time.
The relative position
of the waypoints can be
restricted to satisfy
an approximate curvature constraint.
Waypoint paths are very common,
as they are easy to work with and
can be directly constructed from
state estimates or GPS waypoints
collected in earlier runs
of a particular route.
It is also possible to
define a path using
a sequence of continuous
parameterized curves,
which can be either drawn
from a fixed set of
motion primitives or can be
identified through
optimization during planning.
These curves provide the benefit
of continuously varying motion,
and can be constructed to have
smooth derivatives to aid in
the consistency of error and
error rate calculations.
In all cases of path following,
the controller tries to eliminate
the offset of the vehicle to
the desired path and to
align the vehicle heading
with the path heading.
For each of these paths definitions,
the direction of travel along
the path is also provided,
which can be encoded with the
point ordering or curve ordering.
We will define
these two terms shortly,
as they both play a critical role
in the design of lateral controllers.
Let's now introduced
the two main categories
of lateral control design,
which are widely used
in autonomous vehicles.
The first category of controllers
are geometric controllers,
which rely on the geometry
and coordinates of
the desired path and
the kinematic models of the vehicle.
We'll consider two types
of controllers that are
geometric controllers: the pure
pursuit and the Stanley controllers.
We'll look at these in detail in
the next lessons in this module.
The other category of controllers
is called dynamic controllers.
The most popular
advanced controller in
this category is the model
predictive controller or MPC,
which performs a finite
horizon optimization
to identify the control
command to apply.
MPC is commonly used because of
its ability to handle
a wide variety of
constraints and to identify
optimized solutions that consider
more than just the current errors.
We'll look at MPC design in
the final video in this module.
Let's now investigate the definitions
of errors in path tracking control.
We'll use the kinematic bicycle model
as our basis for this discussion.
So, let's quickly review
the important parameters
of the bicycle model.
The bicycle model is
a suitable control oriented model
of a four-wheel vehicle,
where the front left
and right wheels are
combined into
a single steerable wheel,
and the rear left
and right wheels are
combined together in
a single drive wheel.
For this discussion, we'll use
a line segment as our reference path,
shown as a solid black line
in the diagram.
A dashed black line that is
parallel to the path but
runs through the center of
the front axle is also visible.
For the purposes of lateral control,
we redefine our heading relative
to the current path line segment.
The variable side will
be reused to represent
the relative heading angle of
the vehicle with respect
to the path line.
The front wheel velocity V and
the steering angle relative to
the heading direction delta
do not change,
and are also shown in this diagram.
Note that we can place
a reference frame for
the vehicle at the center
of the rear axle,
at the center of the front axle,
or at the center of gravity
depending on our controller design.
As mentioned in the previous section,
we'll introduce two types of error:
heading and crosstrack error.
The heading error is equal to
the difference between path heading
and vehicle heading at
the reference point along the path.
It is a principal measure
of how well the vehicle is
aligned with and moving in
the direction of the desired path.
The rate of heading
error psi dot helps us
understand how the heading
error evolves over time,
and can be computed from the
kinematic bicycle model equations.
The rate of heading error
can be expressed in
terms of any of the three vehicle
reference points as well.
Here we present the rate
of heading error
relative to the front axle,
as will be used in
the Stanley controller presented
in the third video in this module.
For straight line segments,
the desired heading rate
of change is zero,
and it can be removed.
This is because
the reference heading is
not time-varying for a straight line,
and is in fact equal to zero,
as we have redefined our heading
relative to the current
path direction.
The other type of error is
an offset error called
the crosstrack error.
The crosstrack error is
the distance between
the reference point on
the vehicle and the closest point
on the desired path.
It is the principal
measure of how close
the vehicle's position is to
the desired position along the path.
Both heading error and crosstrack
error must converge to
zero for the vehicle to be properly
tracking the desired path.
The line from the vehicle
reference point to
the path reference point is
perpendicular to the path.
The rate of change of the
crosstrack error can be calculated
by extracting the lateral component
of the forward velocity.
From this equation, we can see
that as the velocity increases,
the crosstrack error
changes more quickly,
meaning that smaller steering
angles are needed to
correct for the same size
crosstrack errors.
Extending this discussion
of the heading and
crosstrack errors to the curved paths
adds some additional complexity,
as it is not immediately clear where
the reference point on
the curved path should lie.
The geometric relations required
fall outside the scope of this video.
We've nonetheless provided links
in the supplemental materials
for those interested in
error calculations
relative to curved paths.
Let's summarize our discussion
of the lateral control concepts.
In this lesson, you've studied
three approaches to defining
reference paths: line segments,
waypoints, and curves.
You've learned how to construct
error metrics for lateral control,
including heading and
crosstrack error.
In the next video,
we'll use these definitions to
construct our first lateral
vehicle controller,
the pure pursuit controller,
to define steering commands that will
track our reference path.
See you there.