Welcome back.
In the last video,
we studied the Stanley controller
for lateral path tracking control.
In this video, we will explore
an advanced applied control strategy,
known as Model Predictive
Control or MPC,
to understand how to incorporate
dynamic modeling into
controller design.
Specifically in this video,
we will describe the MPC architecture
and the concept of
receding horizon control,
formulate an MPC optimization problem
for both linear and nonlinear models,
and apply MPC to joint longitudinal
and lateral vehicle control.
Let's dive in. First, let's
quickly go through the key aspects
of Model Predictive Control.
MPC refers to the control
design approach that
numerically solves an optimization
problem at each time-step.
Because solving an
optimization problem
at each time step can take time,
MPC was originally applied to slow
processes such as
industrial chemical processing.
However, the ever-improving
performance of
today's computing hardware has made
MPC a viable approach even
on embedded hardware.
More and more automotive
applications are
turning to MPC as a way to improve
performance and expand
operating range
for a suite of different
embedded controllers,
from traction control
and stability control,
to emission reduction,
and idle speed control.
Longitudinal and lateral control
for autonomous vehicles is
another extremely suitable
application for MPC.
Model Predictive Control is often
interchangeably referred to
as Receding Horizon Control,
since the controller generates
an actuator signal based on
a fixed finite length horizon at
each time-step which receives
as time moves forward.
The key advantages to solving
online optimizations as part of
the controller are as follows:
The formulation of
an MPC controller is
straightforward requiring
the definition of
an objective function
and relevant constraints
that are then optimized using
well-established solvers.
The states and control signals
can be constrained to stay within
safe operating bounds
and controls can be
selected to maximize
multiple objectives simultaneously.
Both hard constraints and
soft penalties can be employed,
leading to a rich set of solutions
for constrained control problems.
As many automotive subsystems have
rigid actuator constraints and
diverse performance objectives,
MPC has emerged as a major tool
for vehicle control.
The controller can be
explicitly applied to
the linear or non-linear models of
the vehicle and its subsystems,
meaning that we can
use the same approach
even as our models change
or improve over time.
The trade-off these advantages
must be weighed against,
is that MPC requires
significantly more
computational resources
than a Static Control Law.
It is certainly possible to create
optimization formulations
that are too
expensive to compute at
the high update rates required
for smooth vehicle control.
Careful implementation is needed
to avoid overloading processors.
Before we start designing
MPC controllers,
let's take a closer look at
the concept of Receding Horizon.
Receding Horizon Control solves
a fixed size optimization
at each time-step,
which identifies
optimal control inputs
to apply from the current time to
the end of the horizon based on
the objectives constraints and
current state of the vehicle.
One issue that arises in
implementation however,
is that because optimization
can take some amount of time,
the state of the vehicle when
starting the optimization,
will be different from the state of
the vehicle when completing
the optimization.
As a results, we must
use a predicted state in
the optimization for
the time at which
the control input will
actually be applied.
Let's step through the process
and clarify the notation needed.
First, we define the receding
horizon length t. Then,
we set the initial state for
the optimization to be
the predicted state at the end of
the optimization x at time t. Next,
we solve the optimization
as the vehicle
moves from its current
state at time t minus
one to x of t using
the control input identified
in the previous optimization.
Although we won't exactly arrive at
the predicted state at
time t due to disturbances,
we do expect to be reasonably close
if the time interval is short.
Finally, we apply the control
signal from the first time step of
the receding horizon optimization
and repeat the process
for the next time step.
We can visualize the Receding
Horizon or MPC Algorithm,
using the following block
diagram for a control.
We have two main blocks,
an optimizer block,
which is the core MPC component
or a Receding Horizon
Control component,
and the dynamic model.
The model takes in
the past inputs and state
from time t minus one and takes in
the output of the optimizer which is
the current sequence of inputs U
at each time step in the horizon.
The model then outputs predicted
states at the next time-step,
which are compared to
the reference trajectory and
passed into the optimizer as
the future or predicted error.
The optimizer also receives
updated constraints and
the cost function to use,
which can be fixed in advanced or
varied based on changing
operating modes.
The optimizer then solves
its optimization and
the process repeats.
Now, let's take a look at
the linear MPC design in particular.
We use the state space
formulation which
represents a motion
model in discrete form.
The future states
are linearly related
to the current states and
the actuator signals.
Note that, A and B are
the coefficient matrices and are
assumed to be time-invariant.
MPC seeks to find
a control policy U of inputs
over a finite horizon.
If all the states are
to be driven to zero,
the objective function or cost
function when we minimize,
can be defined as follows:
with quadratic error on
both deviations of the state from
zero and on non-zero control inputs.
This is similar to
the optimization problem of
optimal control theory and trades off
control performance and
input aggressiveness.
Note that, the matrices Q
and R are called weight
matrices and can be selected to
achieve a particular
type of response.
If instead we need to track
a reference signals such
as a desired trajectory,
we modify the formulation to include
the error delta x relative
to the desired state.
This is a famous
optimization formulation
and has a closed form solution,
the Linear Quadratic
Regulator or LQR.
The closed form solution
uses full state feedback,
meaning that all states are
used in the control response.
The LQR solution defines
a control gain matrix K,
which can be computed from
the A and B matrices of
the state-space model and
the Q and R matrices
of the cost function.
We've included links in
the supplemental materials to
this fascinating result of
states-pace control theory.
In the more general case,
the objective function is
any differentiable
non-linear function of
a state and inputs over
the receding horizon.
The constraints imposed on
the optimization can include;
non-linear dynamic models of motion,
state and input bounds that
capture things like
maximum steering angles,
and any other inequality
constraints g
are equality constraints
h that affect our system.
For such a general
optimization problem however,
no closed form solution exists.
So, we must rely on numerical
optimization to find a solution.
Even the kinematic bicycle
model falls into this category.
So, almost all MPC controllers
for autonomous driving will
be solved numerically.
Let's now look at
the implementation of
an MPC controller for trajectory
tracking on a self-driving car.
MPC will be used in the same feedback
structure presented earlier,
but we include the conversion from
the tire forces to throttle, break,
and steering commands as a low
level controller inside the loop.
The inputs to the MPC block
or the reference trajectory,
which include the reference
path and velocity,
as well as the vehicle states
at each time step.
The outputs of the MPC block are
the lateral and longitudinal forces
needed to follow
the desired trajectory.
These forces are then translated
into throttle, breaking,
and steering commands, as the output
of the low-level control.
Finally, the actuation signals
are applied to the vehicle
at each time-step,
and a new vehicle state is achieved
closing the feedback loop.
The MPC optimization
will be set up as
follows to perform
a double lane change maneuver.
First, we define a cost for
tracking the desired trajectory,
which includes deviation from
the desired trajectory and
minimization of control
command magnitude.
Next, we define motion
constraints on the vehicle,
which rely on the lateral
and longitudinal models
developed in earlier videos.
We also impose maximum limits
on the tire forces
to restrict them to
fall within the linear tire region to
avoid extreme responses
to control our errors.
These costs and constraints define
the optimization used in our example,
which then gets converted into
actual vehicle commands by
the low-level controller.
It is also possible to incorporate
the low-level control into
the MPC optimization,
which would involve including
as constraints, the engine map,
full vehicle dynamic models,
actuator forces, and
tire force models.
The result is a large
optimization problem
that may be challenging
to solve in real time,
but let's have a look at the results.
This simulation is done for
the double lane change scenario,
where the vehicle first accelerates
to a steady-state speed of
17 meters per second or
60 kilometers per hour,
then maneuvers
four meters to the left,
and returns four meters to
the right immediately thereafter.
The following plots
show the results of
the simulated maneuver
with MPC control,
with the reference trajectory in
blue and the actual
vehicle trajectory in red.
We can see that
the tracking performance with
the MPC controller is excellent,
lagging slightly, but without
overshoot or oscillation.
This is perhaps not
surprising as the simulation
and MPC use the same
model and parameters.
The output of model
predictive controllers,
the lateral and longitudinal forces,
can be seen to be smoothly
varying and well-behaved.
Also, the vehicle yaw rate during
the double lane change
maneuver is plotted,
revealing precise tracking
throughout the states of a vehicle.
MPC shows a lot of promises
a control technique for
autonomous driving and can be
used without modification
for a wide range of
operating conditions and
a large variety of scenarios.
This flexibility and
convenience comes at the cost
of increased computational
requirements and relies
on the availability of
robust optimization solvers to
always return feasible solutions
in the available time window.
Let's summarize what we've
discussed in this video.
We first explored the definition
of Model Predictive Control and
the Receding Horizon and constructed
the closed loop block diagram
for an MPC system.
We then define the costs and
constraints used in MPC.
Finally, we applied MPC to
the trajectory tracking problem
for self-driving cars.
Congratulations, you've made
it to the end of the module.
In this module, you learned how to
define the lateral
path tracking problem,
applied two geometric path
tracking controllers,
the pure pursuit and
Stanley controllers to
the path tracking problem,
and defined a Model Predictive
Controller for joint,
lateral, and longitudinal control.
In the final module in this course,
you'll get your first hands on look
at the Carlos simulator where you'll
design lateral and
longitudinal controllers
to navigate a vehicle
around a race track.